Music Collection, 1848-2003 (bulk 1930s-1980)
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Music collection
1848-2003
1930s-1980
MS 409
9 boxes, 2 volumes, phonograph records (3.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Documents a wide variety of women's participation in the broad field of music. Material consists of books, catalogs, concert programs, interviews (both written and recorded), musical scores, printed material, photographs, publicity, recordings and songbooks. Contains biographical material on well-known women singers and composers (both classical and popular). Includes the women's liberation rock bands and folk music of the late 1960s and early 1970s, as well as feminist recording companies.
This collection contains material that documents a wide variety of women's participation in the broad field of music from the 1840s to 1980. The material consists of articles, books, brochures, catalogs, concert programs, interviews (both written and recorded), leaflets, musical scores, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, photographs, publicity, recordings and songbooks. There are a few items in the collection that date from the nineteenth century including some rather unique items such as a "juvenile singing book" dating from 1853. More typically the nineteenth century material includes biographical articles and newspaper clippings about well-known women singers of the period such as Lillie Greenough and Henriette Sontag, and women composers such as Amy Beach. The most significant of this material relates to internationally known singer Jenny Lind, and especially to the years she spent in Northampton during the 1840s. Included in the Lind material are articles, copies of correspondence, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, concert programs and photographs.
Most of the material in this collection documents the contributions of women musicians to the field after 1930. There is a significant amount of biographical material related to classical musicians such as Nadia Boulanger, Sarah Caldwell, Emmy Destinn, Frederique Petrides, Olga Samaroff Stowkowski, Beverly Sills, Geraldine Farrar, and Kirsten Flagstad. There is also a large amount of material in the collection that documents the achievements and influence of more recent women musicians including folk musicians Malvina Reynolds and Mary Travers; the women's liberation rock bands of the late 1960s and early 1970s; and the early pioneers of feminist "women's music" such as Holly Near, Meg Christian, Alix Dobkin and Margie Adam; as well as feminist recording companies, Redwood Records and Olivia Records.
This collection is organized as follows:
I. General
II. Biographical Material
Oversize Materials
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in the finding aid.
History of the Collection
The Music Collection is an on-going collection comprised of materials that were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
Search Terms
Songbooks, English--United States; Women composers--United States--Sources; Women musicians--United States--Sources; Women--Songs and music; Women's music--History--Sources; Singers--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Adam, Margie; Beach, H. H. A., Mrs., 1867-1944; Boulanger, Nadia; Christian, Meg; Destinnova, Ema, 1878-1930; Dobkin, Alix; Farrar, Geraldine, 1882-1967; Flagstad, Kirsten, 1895-1962; Hegermann-Lindencrone, L. de (Lillie de), 1844-1928; Lind, Jenny, 1820-1887; Near, Holly; Petrides, Frederique, 1903-1983; Raitt, Bonnie; Reynolds, Malvina; Sills, Beverly; Travers, Mary, 1936-; Redwood Records; Olivia Records
Additional Information
Related Material
Related material is located in the following collections in the Sophia Smith Collection: Women's Music Archives Collection, 1975-2005.
Related material is located in the following repositories:
-Amy Beach: University of New Hampshire and University of Missouri-Kansas City
-Nadia Boulanger: Loeb Library, Harvard University
-Geraldine Farrar: Library of Congress
-Kirsten Flagstad: Stanford Archive of Recorded Sound, Stanford University
-Holly Near: Schlesinger Library, Harvard University
-Henriette Sontag: Annenberg Library, University of Pennsylvania
- GENERAL, [see also Oversize Materials]
  - General
    - Women in music, general, 1890s-1990s, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - "A Study of New England Women Composers in the 1880s and 1890s," by Victoria J. O'Reilly (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Women in Music History: A Research Guide" by Jeannie G. Pool, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The Women Troubadours" by Megin Bogin, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Association of Women's Music and Culture (AWMAC), 1990-95 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Catalogs (Box 1)
      - General, 1975-77, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Ladyslipper, Inc., 1980-89 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Meridian Distributors, Inc., 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Composers
    - General, 1925-73, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Women Composers: A Handbook, by Susan Stern, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Conductors, 1930, 1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Directories, 1982, 1991, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Feminist musicians, "Women's Music"
    - General, 1970-77, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Transcripts of interviews with Holly Near, Meg Christian, Margie Adam, Susan Freundlich, and Rosemary Schonfeld: interviews and transcripts by Laura Koplewitz, 1976-80 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Tapes of interviews, 1975-79, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Radical Harmonies," film by Dee Mosbacher, DVD, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Festivals and conferences, 1976-2015, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Opera: Patience and Sarah: A Pioneering Love Story, based on the novel by Isabel Miller, libretto by Wende Persons, Piano/Vocal Score by Paula M. Kimper, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Orchestras
    - General, 1925, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - The Women's Philharmonic, 1992-2003 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Periodicals, [see also Oversize Materials]
    - Curve, Music issue, 1997, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Deneuve the Lesbian Magazine cover stories on Indigo Girls and Ani DiFranco, Feb 1994, Feb 1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Femme musique, Nov/Dec 1994 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Forté: a bold, new direction in music, Vol. 1-4 1984-87 (Box 2A, Folder 1-2)
    - Musica: A Newsletter About Women in Music and the Music in Women, 1974-79 (Box 2A, Folder 3)
    - Sing Out!, Jan/Feb 1971 (Box 2A, Folder 4)
  - Rock musicians and bands, 1971-2015 (Box 2A, Folder 5)
  - Songbooks, 1971-79 (Box 2A, Folder 6)
  - "The Together Sound Book" compiled by Margot McFedries, 1977 (Box 2A, Folder 7)
- BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Miscellaneous, 1858-2002, undated (Box 2B, Folder 1)
  - Amara, Lucine, 1979 (Box 2B, Folder 2)
  - Barbieri, Fedora, 1975 (Box 2B, Folder 3)
  - Beach, Amy, and Mercy Cheney, 1913-74 (Box 2B, Folder 4)
  - Belmont, Eleanor Robson, 1960-69 (Box 2B, Folder 5)
  - Bergen, Charlotte, 1978 (Box 2B, Folder 6)
  - Bond, Carrie Jacobs, [see Oversize Materials] (Box 2B)
  - Boulanger, Nadia, 1958-62, undated (Box 2B, Folder 7)
  - Brico, Antonia, 1935-77 (Box 2B, Folder 8)
  - Caldwell, Sarah, 1971-78 (Box 2B, Folder 9)
  - Coolidge, Elizabeth Sprague, undated (Box 2B, Folder 10)
  - Coolidge, Margaret, 1981 (Box 2B, Folder 11)
  - Crosby, Fanny, 1906-07, undated (Box 2B, Folder 12)
  - Dale, Clamma, 1977 (Box 2B, Folder 13)
  - de los Angeles, Victoria, 1978 (Box 2B, Folder 14)
  - Dessoff, Margarete, 1906 (Box 2B, Folder 15)
  - Destinn, Emmy undated (Box 2B, Folder 16)
  - Dobbs, Mattiwilda, 1956, undated (Box 2B, Folder 17)
  - Dwyer, Doriot Anthony, 1952-79 (Box 2B, Folder 18)
  - Ewing, Maria, 1979 (Box 2B, Folder 19)
  - Farrar, Geraldine [see box 3] (Box 2B)
  - Field, Lucille, 1990 (Box 2B, Folder 20)
  - Fischer, Annie, circa, 1982 (Box 2B, Folder 21)
  - Flagstad, Kirsten [see boxes 4-7] (Box 2B)
  - Garrison, Lucy McKim, 1963 (Box 2B, Folder 22)
  - Gipps, Ruth (conductor/composer), 1962-67, undated (Box 2B, Folder 23)
  - Gomme, Florence C. ("Let Me Rock Your Cradle, Mary"), undated (Box 2C, Folder 1)
  - Homer, Louise, 1903-40, undated (Box 2C, Folder 2)
  - Hopekirk, Helen, 1883 (Box 2C, Folder 3)
  - Horne, Lena, 1950 (Box 2C, Folder 4)
  - Horne, Marilyn, 1971-79 (Box 2C, Folder 5)
  - Jessye, Eva, 1976 (Box 2C, Folder 6)
  - Lang, Margaret Ruthven (composer): obituary, 1972, undated (Box 2C, Folder 7)
  - Le Fan, Nicola, 1974 (Box 2C, Folder 8)
  - Lind, Jenny: clippings, pamphlets, letters, and pictures, 1848-1978, undated (Box 2C, Folder 9-12)
  - Melba, Dame Nellie (Helen Porter Mitchell), 1924 (Box 2C, Folder 13)
  - Mendelssohn, Fanny, undated (Box 2C, Folder 14)
  - Moulton, Mrs. Charles (Lillie Greenough), 1871 (Box 2C, Folder 15)
  - Patti, Adelina, 1919 (Box 2C, Folder 16)
  - Petrides, Frederique, 1935-40, undated (Box 2C, Folder 17)
  - Piazza, Marguerite, 1971 (Box 2C, Folder 18)
  - Raitt, Bonnie, 1972 (Box 2C, Folder 19)
  - Reynolds, Malvina, 1974-75 (Box 2C, Folder 20)
  - Samaroff, Olga (Stokowski), 1939 (Box 2C, Folder 21)
  - Schenk, Janet, 1976 (Box 2C, Folder 22)
  - Sills, Beverly, 1969-79 (Box 2C, Folder 23)
  - Simonata, Giulietta 1959, 1963, undated (Box 2C, Folder 23a)
  - Simone, Nina, undated (Box 2C, Folder 24)
  - Sontag, Henriette, 1852, undated (Box 2C, Folder 25)
  - Stevens, Doris, 1926 (Box 2C, Folder 26)
  - Thursby, Emma, 1927-79, undated (Box 2C, Folder 27)
  - Travers, Mary, 1973 (Box 2C, Folder 28)
  - Tureck, Rosalyn, 1976 (Box 2C, Folder 29)
  - Underhill, Isabel, [see Oversize Materials] (Box 2C)
  - Verrett, Shirley, 1970-76 (Box 2C, Folder 30)
  - Waters, Ethel, 1977 (Box 2C, Folder 31)
  - Webster, Mary Phillips (Box 2C, Folder 32)
  - Farrar, Geraldine (Box 2C)
    - Photographs and clippings, 1882-1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Such Sweet Compulsion (1938) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Flagstad, Kirsten, [see also Oversize Materials] (Box 3)
    - Brochure: pictures (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Biographical information and published photographs, 1936-47, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Clippings, 1937-50, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Programs and concert schedule, 1937-49, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Repertoire of operas, 1940-41 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Programs (Box 4)
      - Carnegie Hall, 1936-47, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Metropolitan Opera, 1935-40 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Articles (originals and photocopies) (Box 4)
      - 1934-37 (Box 5, Folder 8-15)
      - 1938-40 (Box 6, Folder 16-24)
      - 1941-53, undated (Box 7, Folder 25-30)
      - Articles by Oscar Thompson, 1932-45, undated (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Photographs, 1935-47, undated (Box 7, Folder 32)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Phonograph records (Box 8)
    - "Song of Ruth," Mary Howe, undated (Box 8)
    - "…And Ain't I a Woman?" New Harmony Sisterhood Band, 1977 (Box 8)
    - "Ballad of the ERA," Kristan Leurs, 1977 (Box 8)
    - Women's music albums (Chris Williamson and others), circa 1975-89 (Box 8)
  - Calendars (Box 9)
    - The Women's Music Calendar (Cambridge, MA), 1981 and 1982 (Box 9)
    - SDB Manitoba "Ain't I a Woman," 1986 (Box 9)
    - Festival Stage 1st annual women's music calendar, 1994 (Box 9)
  - Periodicals (Box 9)
    - Bitch: The Women's Rock Newsletter With Bite, #5, #6, #10, #12, #15 Jan/Feb, Mar, July 1986 (Box 9)
    - Gay Community News, includng Music Supplement, 6 Jun 1981 (Box 9)
    - Jazz Times, Women in Jazz issue, Aug 1990 (Box 9)
    - Kinesis, Vancouver, BC, music and women issues, 1984-87 (Box 9)
  - Memorabilia: t-shirt, First Annual Midwest Womyn's Autumnfest, undated (Box 9)
  - Biographical materials: daguerreotype of Jenny Lind and Otto Goldschmidt, D. Wells, Northampton, 1852? (Box 10)
  - Beach, Amy (Mrs. H.H.A.): sheet music, 1900-30s, n.d. (Box F)
  - Bond, Carrie Jacobs, "A Perfect Day" and Isabel Underhill, "The Little Brown Nest," undated (Box F)
  - Flagstad, Kirsten: photographs, publicity, schedules, newspaper clippings, 1934-53 (Box F)
  - Edell, Therese: "Peace Piece for Toni Sr"; mounted, undated (Map-case Flat File)